Okay, today's דף daf is מנחות Menachos קא, kuf aleph, 101, triple
digit. We pick up about 15 lines down, line starts the word
למחר lemachar and we pick up starting with מותיב רב הונא בר
מנוח moseiv Rav Huna bar Manoach and we are in the middle
of a discussion of, you know, שמואל Shmuel said that if you
sanctify something like מנחות ונסכים, menachos u-nesachim, the flour, the oil, the
נסכים nesachim that needs to be sanctified in a כלי שרת, kli
sharet, but it has yet to be sanctified in a כלי שרת,
kli sharet, it's going to be offered up on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
you can redeem it while it is still just קדושת דמים kedushat
damim only its value and has not yet קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
because it's not yet in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, you can
redeem it even though it is not טמא. tamei. And although the
משנה mishna says if they became טמא tamei you can redeem it,
that's just because the end of the משנה mishna is saying once
they're in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, then even though they're טמא
tamei you cannot redeem it, and in that way it's different from
an animal, an animal which is קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf can be
redeemed if it has a מום, mum, but this thing which is
a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf through a כלי שרת kli sharet and
is not an animal cannot be redeemed if it is טמא tamei
even though that means it is unusable. And even though the טומאה
tumah might be seen as parallel to a מום. mum. Okay, so
that is the way to read the משנה mishna and the argument
that you can redeem these things even with if they're not טמא,
tamei, if they have not been put in a כלי שרת. kli
sharet. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge this. מותיב
רב הונא בר מנוח moseiv Rav Huna bar Manoach so רב הונא
בר מנוח Rav Huna bar Manoach challenged this. העופות ha-ofot the middle
part of the משנה, mishna, which is a very hard to understand,
it's got a weird list. Here's the middle part of the משנה.
mishna. העופות והעצים והלבונה וכלי שרת, ha-ofot ve-ha-etzim ve-ha-levonah ve-khlei sharet,
so birds and wood and frankincense and כלי שרת, kli sharet, right,
the temple vessels, שנטמאו shenitme'u
that became טמא, tamei, אין להם פדיון ein lahem pidyon you can't
redeem them, שלא נאמר פדיון אלא בבהמה shelo ne'emar pidyon ela be-vehemah
that you can only redeem an animal with a מום. mum. So
that idea that an animal although it has קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
can be redeemed with a מום, mum, you know, that's different, right,
than other things with קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf that cannot become טמא
tamei cannot be redeemed if they're טמא. tamei. But it's a little
unclear what the point of mentioning specifically these things: birds, wood, frankincense
and כלי שרת. kli sharet. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
try to figure that out. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא עופות bishlama ofot קדושת הגוף נינהו.
kedushat haguf ninhu.
So I understand why birds can't be redeemed because they're קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, it's like an animal, it's going to be offered up,
and, you know, with no כלי שרת, kli sharet, they don't even
have the כלי שרת kli sharet of the knife because they're cut
with the fingernail of the כהן. kohen. So that is a קדושת
הגוף kedushat haguf and that cannot be redeemed if it became טמא.
tamei. ולא נאמר אלא בבהמה ve-lo ne'emar ela be-vehemah and the only
thing that has קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf that you can redeem is
a בהמה behemah with a מום. mum. אלא עצים ולבונה וכלי שרת
לפרקו ela etzim u-levonah ve-khlei sharet lipreku
but how about these other things, עצים ולבונה וכלי שרת, etzim u-levonah
ve-khlei sharet,
those are things that don't have קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf have not
been placed in a כלי שרת kli sharet even כלי שרת kli
sharet hasn't been placed in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So why
does the משנה mishna say that you can't redeem it? Very good
question, you know, and it is a weird list, what is it
about the things on this list? אלא לאו משום דטהורים בעלמא ela
lav mishum de-tehorim be-alma
so I know what the point of this list is, maybe with
the exception of birds. You know, the point of this list is
that these are things which don't really become טמא. tamei. אלא משום
דטהורים בעלמא אין נפדים ela mishum de-tehorim be-alma ein nifdim
so it must be the principle that normally you can't redeem things
that are טהור tahor against what שמואל Shmuel said. והני נמי ve-hanei
nami and even though the משנה mishna says when these become טמא
tamei you cannot redeem them, אף af the point is and the
reason these specifically are listed is אף על גב דנטמאו כטהורים דמו.
af al gav de-nitme'u ke-tehorim damu. Even when they become טמא, tamei,
they really are like they are still טהור. tahor. Okay, what does
this mean? So the גמרא Gemara will explain. So let's
see. דעצים ולבונה de-etzim u-levonah because when it comes to wood and
frankincense, לאו בני אשוויי אוכלא נינהו lav benei ashvuyei okhla ninhu those
are not really edible, you know, so if and therefore they shouldn't
be able to become טמא. tamei. אלא חיבת הקודש משויא להו אוכלא
ela hibat ha-kodesh mashvya lehu okhla
it's because of the what's called the dearness of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash that it's treated as if it is food and it
is therefore treated as if it became טמא tamei even though it
is not genuinely טמא. tamei. Alright? דעצים de-etzim
and also when it comes to and when it comes to the
wood, okay, I'm sorry. דעצים ולבונה לאו
בני אשוויי. de-etzim u-levonah lav benei ashvuyei. אלא חיבת הקודש משויא להו
אוכלא. ela hibat ha-kodesh mashvya lehu okhla. דעצים כמה דלא משפי להו
לגזרין de-etzim kama de-la mashfei lehu le-gizrin
as long as you have not smoothed them out to be like,
you know, logs that you're going to use on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
לא מיכשרי lo makhshiri they are not considered yet fit for becoming
טמא. tamei. Now why is wood anyway fit for becoming טמא tamei
if it's not a כלי? kli? But we learn out from a
פסוק pasuk that it says והבשר ve-ha-basar לרבות עצים ולבונה le-rabot etzim
u-levonah that wood and frankincense do become טמא tamei because again what
the גמרא Gemara is saying: חיבת הקודש, hibat ha-kodesh, there's a special
הלכה halacha that they're being used in the context of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and therefore they can become טמא. tamei. but only
at a certain state. Wood only when it is smoothed out and
ready to be put on as a log. And if it has
not yet been put on as a log, it can't really become
טמא tamei מדרייתא. mid'raita.
So, okay. לבונה נמי, Levona nami, and by the frankincense, כמה דלא
קדשה בכלי שרת, kama d'lo kidsha bichli shares, לא מתכשרא, lo miskashra,
and as long as it's not in a כלי שרת, kli shares,
it's not yet similarly in the state of being fit to be
put on the מזבח. mizbeiach. So, if these things have not been
put in a כלי שרת, kli shares, they are fund- even though
there's a חידוש chiddush that the wood and the frankincense can become
טמא, tamei, but not at the state that they're in right now.
So fundamentally, even if they touch טומאה, tuma, we might call them
טמא, tamei, but they're really still טהור. tahor. Okay? And כלי שרת
נמי, kli shares nami, and a כלי שרת, kli shares, which is
the the third thing there. הואיל ואית להו טהרה במקוה, ho'il v'is
lehu tahara b'mikvah, since it's got a- since you can put it
in the מקוה, mikvah, it's also is not
really טמא. tamei. I mean, it is טמא, tamei, but it can
be fixed. Excuse me, I put that לא lo in the wrong
place. The לא lo is part of the next sentence. Anyway, so
it says כלי שרת נמי הואיל ואית להו טהרה במקוה. kli shares
nami ho'il v'is lehu tahara b'mikvah. And they can be put into
a מקוה. mikvah. Okay? So therefore their טומאה tuma is not really
a permanent status. So therefore what? So what we are saying is,
why does this list in this משנה mishna list these things? To
say that these things can't be redeemed if they become טמא. tamei.
So, a bird we understand, it's קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, fine. But
how about these other things? Okay? So why can't they? They're not
yet קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf if they haven't been put in a
כלי שרת. kli shares. So it's saying it must be because fundamentally
you're only allowed to redeem something that is טמא, tamei, even if
it only has קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, not if it's fundamentally טהור,
tahor, okay, against שמואל. Shmuel. And a כלי שרת kli shares can
become טהור, tahor, you put it in a מקוה, mikvah, so you're
not allowed to redeem it because it's not really טמא, tamei, it's
not stuck there. And these other things, ironically, even though we treat
them as טמא, tamei, they fundamentally are still טהור. tahor. And therefore,
even though practically we're not gonna let you use them, since they're
not really טמא, tamei, then you don't have an allowance to be
פודה. podeh. Okay. So
that
read of the משנה mishna explains this middle list. What is this
middle list about? Why is it being singled out? Because to tell
you that you can't redeem things when they are טהור, tahor, even
though they don't have קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, and these things are
fundamentally in the טהור tahor category. Okay, that's the argument. So let's
see how the גמרא gemara responds. So the גמרא gemara
says לא. lo. The גמרא gemara says like this, לא, lo, no,
that's not the right read. לעולם אימא לך, Le'olam eima lach, I'll
tell you, טהור בעלמא נפדין, tahor be'alma nifdin, that שמואל Shmuel is
right. You can redeem things that are טהור. tahor. והני משום דלא
שכיחי הוא. V'hani mishum d'lo shechichi hu.
And the reason you can't redeem these things
when they is because they are not so common. Meaning what? Meaning
I agree with your reading of the משנה mishna that these things,
because they're טהור, tahor, can't be redeemed. But I- or quasi-טהור. tahor.
But I don't agree with your reading that that means that the
general rule is that טהור tahor things cannot be redeemed. These things
the רבנן rabbanan did not want to let you redeem them because
they're not so common. Frankincense, who has frankincense?
I mean, the גמרא gemara will ask about wood. Okay, who has
כלי שרת? kli shares? Those are things that are not so common.
And therefore if you sanctify them, the רבנן rabbanan don't want you
redeeming them. They want those to get to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Finally, somebody sanctified some frankincense. So now that's therefore they said
these uncommon things as long as they are טהור, tahor, we're not
gonna let you redeem them, but it's only these specific, it's not
a general rule. Okay, so let's see that.
So it says like this, והני משום דלא שכיחי הוא. V'hani mishum
d'lo shechichi hu. So the גמרא gemara says,
one minute. בשלמא לבונה
וכלי שרת, Bishlama levona v'kli shares, frankincense and holy vessels, לא שכיחי,
lo shechichi, I get that those are uncommon. Once they're sanctified, unless
they became טמא tamei or כלי שרת kli shares even if it
becomes טמא, tamei, whatever, once they're sanctified, we don't want you to
redeem them. Okay, so those the רבנן rabbanan said we're not gonna
let you redeem if they are טהור. tahor. Okay, אלא עצים משכח
שכיחי, ela etzim meshkach shechichi,
but עצים, etzim, those are common. So if those are common, why
shouldn't you be allowed to redeem them if they are טהור? tahor?
So the גמרא gemara says, עצים נמי כיון דאמר מר כל עץ
שנמצא בו תולעת פסול לגבי מזבח, etzim nami keivan d'amar mar kol
etz shenimtza bo tolaat pasul legabei mizbeiach,
even by wood, wood having wood that can be used on the
מזבח mizbeiach is not so common because we teach that even if
there's like a little worm in the wood, you can't use it
on the מזבח. mizbeiach. הלכך לא שכיחי. Hilchach lo shechichi. So wood
that is fit for the מזבח mizbeiach is not so common. Okay,
so we have two reads of the משנה, mishna, right? Why does
the משנה mishna mention these little this middle list of things? things
that can't be redeemed if they're טמא, tamei, and presumably even though
they only have קדושת דמים kedushas damim and normally you can redeem
things with קדושת דמים? kedushas damim? So read number one is because
they really are fundamentally טהור tahor and you're not allowed to redeem
things that are טהור, tahor, okay, even only with קדושת דמים. kedushas
damim. Read number two is
the
rabbis didn't want you to redeem these things when they were טהור
tahor because they want them to be used for the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So these things in particular are rare, they want them
to be used, they did not want you to redeem them when
they were טהור. tahor. And therefore, you know, they're not even going
to let you redeem them when they are טמא tamei as well,
maybe again because they're not really טמא tamei at all. Whatever it
is, these are things that the rabbis did not want you to
redeem because they're not common, and it's only this list. There's no
general rule that you can't redeem things that are טהור. tahor. Those
are the two readings. Okay, so now let's see where the גמרא
gemara goes with
it. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, אשמעיה לשמואל, ishmieh leShmuel, הא
דתניא, ha detanya, if שמואל Shmuel had heard that which we teach,
which we taught in a ברייתא, beraisa, המתפיס תמימים לבדק הבית אין
פודים אותם אלא למזבח, hamatfis temimim lebedek habayis ein podin osam ela
lemizbeach, that if somebody grabs, the word המתפיס, hamatfis, but basically takes
something that is a perfect, you know, cow or sheep without a
blemish and rather than saying I'm going to sanctify this as a
קרבן, korban, says I'm going to donate it to the temple proceeds,
בדק הבית, bedek habayis, like basically, you know, let the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash sell it and use the money for whatever they want,
okay, for operating expenses. So the הלכה halacha is when the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash sells it or when the owner redeems it, you
know, let's say you're going to sell it to somebody, you know,
who wants a cow or wants a sheep, only sell it to
somebody, אין פודים אלא למזבח, ein podin ela lemizbeach, who wants to
use it for a קרבן. korban. Okay, so you can't use this
for a קרבן, korban, the owner sanctified it for the proceeds to
be used for operating expenses of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash will take the cow, you know, it
used to be cars for kids, here it's cows for מקדש, Mikdash,
they take the cow and they're going to sell it, use that
money to, I don't know, do some repairs. But they're only going
to sell the cow and then the קדושה kedusha will transfer to
the money. But they're only going to sell the cow to somebody
who needs to bring a קרבן, korban, and then he will take
it, sanctify it and bring it as a קרבן. korban. Okay, he'll
give it a new sanctity and make it a קרבן. korban. Why
is this true? Because שכל הראוי למזבח אינו יוצא מידי מזבח לעולם.
shekol haraui lemizbeach eino yotzei miyedei mizbeach leolam. Anything that is fit
for the מזבח, mizbeach, we don't want it to escape the מזבח.
mizbeach. This was sanctified, it could be used as a קרבן, korban,
even though the sanctity wasn't that type of sanctity, we want to
ensure that it gets used as a קרבן. korban. Okay, now he
says, one minute, let's analyze this case of the cow. ואף על
גב דקדושת דמים נינהו, veaf al gav dekedushas damim ninhu, it was
only sanctified for its value, the whole point was it had to
be sold, it itself did not have yet a קדושת הגוף, kedushas
haguf, ואין נפדים, ve-ein nifdim, the principle is we do not want
to let you redeem it or certainly not redeem it in a
way that is going to get this out away from the מזבח.
mizbeach. Okay, הוי טהורים הם, hovei tehorim hem, since it is טהור,
tahor, this can be used on the מזבח, mizbeach, we want to
ensure that it continues to get used on the מזבח. mizbeach. So
that's a case of קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, the way it'll be
used on the מזבח mizbeach is we sell it and then the
person resanctifies it as a קרבן. korban. But that's the goal, to
use it on the מזבח. mizbeach. So if that's true, that exact
same logic should dictate by the מנחה ונסכים. mincha venesachim. You actually
those you did sanctify to use on the מזבח, mizbeach, right now
they have קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, but as long as they are
טהור, tahor, you can put them in a כלי שרת kli shares
and then put them on the מזבח. mizbeach. So something that is
טהור tahor that has been sanctified with קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, we
want to see it make its way to the מזבח. mizbeach. That's
why the cow has to be reused, and that's why this case
of מנחה ונסכים mincha venesachim you should not be allowed to redeem
it and you should have to go ahead and put it in
a כלי שרת. kli shares. So if שמואל Shmuel had heard that
ברייתא, beraisa, he would have realized that the same logic applies to
our משנה mishna and you can't redeem them when they are טהור.
tahor. And the גמרא gemara says like this, הוי תמימים וטהורים הם
הוה הדר ביה, hovei temimim utehorim hem hava hadar bei, if he
had heard this he would have reversed himself. So the גמרא gemara
says: ולא היא, velo hi, it's not true. אשמעיה ולא הדר ביה,
ishmieh velo hadar bei, he knows about this ברייתא beraisa and he
did not reverse himself. Why? Why is this ברייתא beraisa an exception?
לאו אמרת התם כיון דלא שכיחי לא מפרקי? lav amart hasom kevan
delo shchichi lo mifriki? We just got through explaining that the way
שמואל Shmuel would explain this list in the מזבח mizbeach about about
the משנה, mishna, about the לבונה levona and the wood and so
on is there are some things we don't want you to redeem,
we want to make sure they get to the מזבח, mizbeach, okay,
and that's that middle list in the משנה. mishna. So once that's
true, הכא נמי כיון דשכיחי מומים דפסלי בבהמה, hacha nami kevan deshchichi
mumim depaslei bebehema,
since it's common to have blemishes that make an animal invalid, דאפילו
בדוקין שבעין נמי פסלי, deafilu bedukin sheba'ayin nami paslei,
even if it's some type of a film in the eye that
would invalidate it, הלכך לא שכיחי, hilkach lo shchichi, therefore it's not
common. So what we've done here is, and therefore because it's rare
to have an unblemished animal, we want to ensure it makes its
way to the
מזבח. mizbeach. basically doing is as opposed to a principle that anything
that is טהור, tahor, we want to ensure it gets to the
מזבח mizbe'ach and you can't redeem it as long as it's טהור,
tahor, what we are saying what שמואל Shmuel is saying is no,
as a general rule you can redeem טהור tahor things, but if
something is sanctified and טהור, tahor, and you know, and is rare,
that we do want to ensure gets to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
that's an unblemished animal, you know, that is frankincense, wood, etc., but
you know what it isn't? It isn't wine and flour. Those things
in the משנה, Mishna, those we it's okay you want to redeem
it and use something else. So the things that don't get redeemed
are the things that we really like want to hold on to.
Okay, so that's so, so let's take a look where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this. רב כהנא אמר טמאים נפדים טהורים אין נפדים.
Rav Kahana amar tme'im
nifdim tehorim ein nifdim.
So רב כהנא Rav Kahana takes the position that we've been sort
of the you know trying to argue against
שמואל. Shmuel. Sorry, you can only redeem טמא tamei things, not טהור
tahor things, okay, and that's the explanation of the middle cases in
the משנה, Mishna, that's the explanation of the בהמה behema that you
know you have to make sure gets its way to the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. You don't redeem things that are טהור tahor even only קדושת
דמים. kedushat damim. וכן אמר רבי אושעיא, v'chen amar Rabi Oshaya, רבי
אושעיא Rabi Oshaya said the same thing, טמאים נפדים טהורים אין נפדים,
tme'im nifdim tehorim ein nifdim, only טמא tamei things. איכא דאמרי אמר
רב אושעיא, Ika d'amri amar Rav Oshaya, some say רב אושעיא Rav
Oshaya say אפילו טהורים נפדים, afilu tehorim nifdim, no, like שמואל, Shmuel,
in principle you can redeem טהור tahor things with only קדושת דמים.
kedushat damim. And some things maybe not because we you know they're
rare, but fundamentally yes. רבי אליעזר אומר כולם טמאים נפדים טהורים אין
נפדים. Rabi Eliezer omer kulam tme'im nifdim tehorim ein nifdim. Everything,
I basically I agree with the earlier positions, you can only redeem
things if they're טמא, tamei, not if they're טהור, tahor, חוץ, chutz,
but there's one thing you can redeem if it is טהור. tahor.
מעשירית האיפה של מנחת חוטא, me'asirit ha'eifa shel minchat chotei,
the you know the מנחה mincha of a sinner in the קרבן
עולה ויורד korban oleh v'yored at the end of פרשת ויקרא Parshat
Vayikra that if somebody does certain types of sins, not these are
very a small number of sins, then he brings you know certain
קרבן korban of of like a sheep, but if like what but
but if he doesn't have the money then he brings birds, and
if he doesn't have the money he brings a מנחה. mincha. Alright,
so in that case you sanctified this מנחה mincha because you did
that sin and you're you sanctified this and it has not yet
been put in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, there you can redeem
it if you become wealthier and now can afford to bring the
bird. שהרי אמרה תורה מחטאתו על חטאתו. sheharei amra Torah mechata'to al
chata'to. So as when the תורה Torah talks about it, you know,
it says you know he shall bring from his חטאת chatat on
his חטאת chatat and from there we learn that if you set
aside money to you know for a big קרבן, korban, a sheep,
and then you became poorer, so then you can actually take a
subset of that money and use it to buy you know the
bird, or if you set aside money for a bird and you
became poor you take a subset מחטאתו mechata'to a subset and use
it to buy the מנחה. mincha. We're not going to force you
to buy something that you now can't afford even though when you
designated the money you were at that level. Similarly על חטאתו al
chata'to is telling you that if you set aside money for a
מנחה mincha or you sanctified a מנחה, mincha, that's why it's relevant
here, and now you got richer, now you have to add על
חטאתו al chata'to and bring the next level, the bird, okay, or
the bird you go up to you know the sheep. So there
because the תורה Torah wants you to do what is your current
level, not the level you were at when you sanctified it, so
there if it is טהור tahor you can go ahead and you
know redeem it so that you can bring up the next level.
Okay. אמר רבי אושעיא amar Rabi Oshaya now what's not clear here
is all of these restrictions that you cannot redeem when you are
when it is טהור, tahor, is that Rabbinic, is that דאורייתא? de'oraita?
Certainly the whole idea that it's rare and we want to keep
our hands on it is Rabbinic. But the more categorical positions you
know that you can't do it if it's טהור, tahor, we're not
quoting any פסוקים, psukim, so it does seem that this is all
Rabbinic, this des- you know that you can't do it, which makes
it interesting quoting these פסוקים, psukim, but it might be saying the
Rabbis' restriction not to redeem when it's טהור, tahor, they didn't apply
to this, this we need to keep the תורה's Torah principle that
you can move up and down the ladder. Okay. אמר רבי אושעיא,
amar Rabi Oshaya, said רבי אושעיא, Rabi Oshaya, שמעתי פיגול במנחה לרבי
שמעון אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין.
shamati pigul b'mincha l'Rabi Shimon eino
metamei tumat ochlin. I heard
the sounds like it's not going to be relevant, but we'll circle
back. I heard that if somebody did a פיגול pigul when he
was offering up a מנחה, mincha, you know he took the קמיצה
kmitza and he thought to eat the מנחה mincha the wrong time
and so on,
according to רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon,
then that מנחה mincha that is now פיגול pigul cannot become טמא
tamei as food. Why? Because we're going to see רבי שמעון Rabi
Shimon says something to have the status of food to become טמא,
tamei, you know as food stuffs can become טמא tamei when it
touches something טמא, tamei, is only something that is edible. And because
and this because it's פיגול pigul and you're not allowed to eat
it, it's considered like it's not edible. All right, if that's רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position, this would seem to be an obvious application.
But now let's see how we know it's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon
position and why this might not be such an obvious application. Okay,
דתנן, detnan, we've taught in the משנה: Mishnah: ערלה וכלאי הכרם, orlah
ve'kilai hakerem, you have ערלה, orlah, right, tree within the first three
years, or
כלאי הכרם, kilai hakerem, כלאיים kilayim of a vineyard that you know
it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, השור הנסקל והעגלה ערופה, hashor haniskal ve'ha'eglah
arufa, these are all things that are אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, an
ox that gored and that you have to stone
it or an עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, an animal, you know, you
break the neck of the calf because you don't know who murdered
this person, וציפורי מצורע, vetzipporei metzora, the birds of a מצורע metzora
that you, you know, you use to go ahead and, you know,
and purify the מצורע metzora with it, that you שחט shacht those
birds, okay, ופטר חמור ufeter chamor and the case of a donkey
that the firstborn of a donkey if you don't want to redeem
it with a sheep then you break its neck and it's אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, ובשר בחלב uvasar bechalav and meat and milk, all
these things are not just I should say אסור באכילה assur ba'achilah
but they're also אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, you're not even allowed to
derive benefit from it. Okay, כולם מטמאים טומאת אוכלים, kulam metame'im tumat
ochlim, all of them can be טמא tameh as foodstuff. Now by
the way רש''י Rashi just says like how does a שור הנסקל,
shor haniskal, why do you have to say it's טמא tameh as
food if you stone it, whatever, then it's a נבלה, neveilah, it's
טמא tameh as
a נבלה, neveilah, עגלה ערופה egla arufa the same thing. So anyway
there's one case, the easiest understanding is you went ahead and you
שחט shacht it, you didn't stone it, you didn't break its neck,
but even so it was at a stage where it was אסור
בהנאה assur behana'ah even though it was שחט shacht rather than stoned
or had its neck broken. Okay, so that's not exactly our topic,
we won't go in there, but that's the point, so these things
would not be treated as food, oh excuse me, are treated as
food even though they're אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, that's the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. רבי שמעון אומר כולם אין מטמאים טומאת אוכלים, Rabbi Shimon
omer kulam ein metame'im tumat ochlim, nope, they can't, they're not treated
as food because they're אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. ומוודה רבי שמעון בבשר
בחלב שמטמא טומאת אוכלים Umodeh Rabbi Shimon bevasar bechalav shemetameh tumat ochlim
except with meat and milk. Why? הואיל והיתה לו שעת הכושר Ho'il
vehayetah lo she'at hachosher because something, it didn't start its life as
meat and milk cooked together, it started life as meat and as
milk, and those two things were, you know, were מותר muttar to
be eaten, and even if you combined them, let's say you soaked
them together, before you cooked them together, it was all still מותר.
muttar. So because at a certain stage in its life it was
it was it was מותר בהנאה muttar behana'ah and able to be
eaten, even when it becomes אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah it continues being
food. But everything else that was never able to be eaten and
never and always אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, even these cows or whatever,
by the time they were, you know, a live cow, you're not
allowed to eat a live cow, so even though it started its
life not being a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, it never existed as
food without being אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. All right, so that's רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. Anything that started as food and started when
it started as food was אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah is not הלכתית
halachically food and cannot become טמא. tameh.
All right. ואמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rav Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan, okay, so that's that principle that it's not food. מה
טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mah ta'ama deRabbi Shimon? What's the reason of רבי
שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? מכל האוכל אשר יאכל, Mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel, the
פסוק passuk speaks when it speaks about like a שרץ sheretz touching
food, it says from all food that can be eaten. אוכל שאתה
יכול להאכילו לאחרים קרוי אוכל, Ochel she'atah yachol le'achilo la'acherim karui ochel,
food that can be fed to others, meaning non-Jews, that you can
at least get some הנאה hana'ah out of it, maybe you personally
don't have to eat it, but as long as you can get
some הנאה, hana'ah, feed it to non-Jews, feed it to your dog,
that is, you know, קרוי אוכל, karui ochel, that's called food. אוכל
שאי אתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים, Ochel she'ei attah yachol le'achilo la'acherim, if
you can't feed it to non-Jews because it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah,
אינו קרוי אוכל, eino karui ochel, is not food. Okay, so a
simple position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. For something to be called
food for laws of טומאה, tumah, it has to be מותר בהנאה.
muttar behana'ah. Now, by the way, תוספות Tosafot asks an interesting question.
Why don't you say it has to be מותר באכילה? muttar ba'achilah?
Why are you being so and once you're דרש darshing the פסוק
passuk אשר יאכל asher ye'achel that can be eaten, why don't you
say that it has to be totally permissible to be eaten, not
only permissible to derive benefit? So you take a look at this
תוספות: Tosafot: אוכל שאי אתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים, Ochel she'ei attah yachol
le'achilo la'acherim, תוספות Tosafot says here בשם רבי אליעזר ממיץ, beshem Rabbi
Eliezer miMitz, the יראים, Yere'im, דהכא לא ממעט רבי שמעון מדכתיב אשר
יאכל אלא איסור הנאה, dehacha lo mema'et Rabbi Shimon midechtiv asher ye'achel
ella issur hana'ah, here he's only excluding איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, that,
okay, but other food other things that are אסור באכילה, assur ba'achilah,
you know, are still considered food. ובפרק כיסוי הדם ממעט רבי שמעון
אף טרפה מכיסוי משום דכתיב אשר יאכל Uveperek Kissui Hadam mema'et Rabbi
Shimon af tereifah mikissui mishum dechtiv asher ye'achel ולא מן איסור הנאה
דווקא. velav min issur hana'ah davka. In another place he uses the
word which shall be eaten to exclude even things that are forbidden
to be eaten. So here's the answer: ויש לומר דהכא כתיב מכל
האוכל, Veyesh lomar dehacha kativ mikol ha'ochel, the משמע mashma כל kol
לרבויי. leribbuyei. Since it says from all food that can be eaten,
the suggestion is it's a pretty large category. So if he's going
to exclude something, it'll only be the most severe food that can't
even be eaten by others. Okay, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
food, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says I don't care whether it's
permissible or not, if it's edible, it's food. And רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says it has to be somebody has to be able to
eat it. Maybe not a Jew, but somebody, it has to be
מותר בהנאה. muttar behana'ah. Okay, so now let's continue.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי Ee hachi
says, I'm sorry,
hold on, אינו כאוכל. einoh ke-ochel. הפיגא במנחה נמי אוכל היא hapiga
b'Mincha nami ochel hi דהכיל לאחריה. de-hachil le-acharei. Okay, so this case
of פיגול pigul is food that is אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it's
פיגול, pigul, so therefore it can't become טמא טומאת אוכלין. tamei tumat
ochlin. Now, you're probably thinking one minute, this started its life without
being פיגול. pigul. Okay, so we'll get there. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי הכי בשר בחלב נמי תיפוק ליה דאוכלא דאתה יכול להאכילו
לאורחים הוא.
Ee hachi basar bechalav nami teipokelei d'ochla d'ata
yachol leha'achilo l'archaim hu. דתניא, De-tanya, so okay, so before we get
to challenging that's our argument, we want to first better understand רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, okay? So it says like this, you know, as
long as we're talking about רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, why did he
have to say בשר בחלב basar bechalav is okay, you know, can
be, is food because it started its life as being מותר? muttar?
There's another reason he could say it's food. According to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon himself, בשר בחלב basar bechalav is not אסור בהנאה. assur
behana'ah. Okay, so let's take a look. אי הכי בשר בחלב נמי
תיפוק ליה דאוכלא דאתה יכול להאכילו לאורחים הוא. Ee hachi basar bechalav
nami teipokelei d'ochla d'ata yachol leha'achilo l'archaim hu. So before we get
to analyzing your statement about
פיגול, pigul, why if we're talking about רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, what
problem is it even why are we even talking about בשר בחלב?
basar bechalav? According to him you can feed that to others. דתניא,
De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי שמעון יהודה אומר משום
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון יהודה
Rabbi Shimon Yehuda says in the name of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, בשר בחלב אסור באכילה מותר בהנאה, basar bechalav
assur be-achila muttar behana'ah, that בשר בחלב basar bechalav yes, you can't
eat it but you can derive benefit. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk
says, כי עם קדוש אתה להשם אלקיך לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו,
Ki am kadosh ata l'Hashem Elokecha, lo tivashel g'di b'chalev imo, you're
a holy people, don't cook meat in its mother's milk. ולהלן הוא
אומר ואנשי קדש תהיון לי, U-l'halan hu omer ve'anshei kodesh tihyu li,
the same word of קדש, kodesh, עם קדוש, am kadosh, אנשי קדש,
anshei kodesh, you're a holy people. ובשר בשדה טרפה לא תאכלו, Uvasar
basade tereifa lo tocheilu, don't eat a טרפה. tereifa. מה להלן, Ma
le-halan, just as there by a טרפה tereifa it uses the word
קדש kodesh but the only thing that is off-limits is eating it,
not הנאה, hana'ah, we know that from elsewhere. מה להלן אסור באכילה
מותר בהנאה, Ma le-halan assur be-achila muttar behana'ah, you can't eat it
but you can get הנאה. hana'ah. אף כאן, Af kan, so even
the אנשי קדש anshei kodesh of בשר בחלב אסור באכילה מותר בהנאה,
basar bechalav assur be-achila muttar behana'ah, you can get הנאה. hana'ah. So
why are we even discussing בשר בחלב basar bechalav according to רבי
שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? You can get הנאה hana'ah according to him. That's
not how we פוסקן, pasken, but that's how he holds. So the
גמרא Gemara says חדא ועוד קאמר. Chada ve-od ka'amar. He's saying yes,
one plus. I got two reasons why בשר בחלב basar bechalav isn't
a problem for me. חדא, Chada, number one, דאוכלא דאתה יכול להאכילו
לאורחים הוא. d'ochla d'ata yachol leha'achilo l'archaim hu. My personal position is
בשר בחלב basar bechalav is מותר בהנאה. muttar behana'ah. That's why I'm
not bothered with it, you can feed it to other people. ועוד,
Ve-od, number two, לדידי נמי היתה לו שעת הכושר. l'didi nami hayta
lo sha'at hakoher. Even according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kama who
thinks it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, I would still agree with בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav. Why? Because it started off being מותר. muttar. Okay,
so that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. You know, an interesting position
about בשר בחלב, basar bechalav, but his basic position is אסור בהנאה
assur behana'ah cannot become טמא tamei as food unless like בשר בחלב
basar bechalav it started off its life בהיתר. be-heter. And now we're
going to say, so for that reason, a מנחה Mincha that's פיגול
pigul is also not considered food for laws of טומאת אוכלין. tumat
ochlin. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מתיבי, Meitivei, they asked
on this. רבי שמעון אומר יש נותר שהוא מטמא טומאת אוכלין ויש
נותר שאינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין, Rabbi Shimon omer: Yesh notar she-metamei tumat
ochlin ve-yesh notar she-eino metamei tumat ochlin, that there is נותר, notar,
a קרבן korban that was left over and now can't be eaten
and has to be burned. Sometimes it's treated as food and can
become טמא tamei if something טמא tamei touches it, and sometimes it's
not treated as food. What's the difference? כיצד? Keitzad? לן לפני זריקה
אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין, לאחר זריקה מטמא טומאת אוכלין.
Lan lifnei zerika eino metamei tumat
ochlin, l'achar zerika metamei tumat ochlin. If it, you know, stayed overnight
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash without the blood ever being sprinkled
for this קרבן, korban, then what's the story? This meat was never
able to be eaten. From the moment it was
שחט shechted and it became meat, it couldn't be eaten because the
blood hadn't been thrown on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And then before the
blood gets thrown on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's the next day. At that point the blood can't
get thrown anyway. So this meat never became fit to be eaten.
That case it would not be food. לאחר זריקה, L'achar zerika, but
if you sprinkled the blood on the מזבח mizbe'ach and then the
כהנים Kohanim could eat the meat, and they didn't get around to
eating it, and they left it till the next morning, in that
case מטמא טומאת אוכלין, metamei tumat ochlin, it would be טמא טומאת
אוכלין. tamei tumat ochlin. Why? The same point about בשר בחלב, basar
bechalav, because there was a part of its life where it was
permissible to be eaten. So here he says, you know, that point
of בשר בחלב basar bechalav here is now said in a קרבן
korban context. And once you're making that point, that should be true
about the מנחה Mincha too. The מנחה Mincha was able to be
eaten when it was flour and water. You can't say that about
an animal. An animal starts when it was שחט. shechted. But the
מנחה Mincha had a time when it could be eaten. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. ופיגול, U'pigul, so בין בקדשי קדשים
בין בקדשים קלים אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין, bein b'kodshei kodashim bein b'kodashim
kalim eino metamei tumat ochlin, פיגול במנחה מטמא טומאת אוכלין. pigul b'Mincha
metamei tumat ochlin. And now even actually I jumped ahead, the ברייתא
Baraita itself, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself says the case of פיגול,
pigul, and he distinguishes between animals and the מנחה. Mincha. If you're
having an animal sacrifice and you have a פיגול pigul thought, okay,
so then again, the meat is never permissible. As soon as the
כהן kohen had a פיגול pigul thought at any stage between שחיטה
shechita and throwing of the blood, the animal is going to become
אסור assur and when it became meat, it never had a moment
of being מותר. muttar. So פיגול pigul by animals, it's not food.
But here, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon explicitly is saying פיגול pigul by
a מנחה mincha is food because before you did the פיגול, pigul,
it was edible as flour and as flour and oil. So how-
so how did you make your statement about a מנחה? mincha? Now
we understand the חידוש chiddush of the מנחה mincha because- but it's
such a חידוש chiddush that it seems like it's not true. רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon is explicitly saying that by a מנחה mincha it
is considered food. So let's see what it answers. לא קשיא. lo
kashya. כאן שהייתה לו שעת הכושר כאן שלא הייתה לו שעת הכושר.
kan shehaysa lo shas hakosher kan
shelo haysa lo shas hakosher. When- when you know, when it was
being said, when רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya was saying that it did
not have- it wasn't food, he was talking about a very special
case where it never was able to be eaten, even when- even
be- you know, even before it became sanctified and so on. How
could that be? It was flour and oil. So let's take a
look. So in one case it did not have a שעת הכושר
shas hakosher time when it was fit to be eaten, and in
the other case it had a time when it was fit to
be eaten. So what's the case? היכי דמי דלא הייתה לו שעת
הכושר? heichi dami delo haysa lo shas hakosher? How do you get
this case of flour and oil that never were fit to be
eaten?
דהקדישנו במחובר. dehikdishanu bimchubar. You sanctified them when it was still wheat
and when the olives were still like on the tree. So because
it was קודש kodesh at that time, it never had a time
where it was fit to be eaten. And then by the time
you made it into a קרבן korban etc., it was gonna be
fit to be eaten finally when the oil was pressed and the
wheat was turned into flour and was brought as a קרבן korban
and- and this is how you sanctified it way way back. And
then when the קומץ kometz is brought, then you'll be able to
eat from it. But until that point, from the very beginning of
its life, it was never able to be eaten. That would be
the scenario about- okay, it's a bit hard to read that into
רב אושעיא, Rav Oshaya, but that's what we're claiming. And now we're
going to see why this is relevant for our discussion. So the
גמרא Gemara says, וליפרקינהו? velifrikinhu? So even in that scenario, wonderful, you
sanctified the olives on the tree and the grain growing from the
ground, you have the ability to redeem it. Okay? And that ability
to redeem it should mean that the food is considered able to
be eaten because the potential to eat it means you have the
potential of being able to be eaten. Now, so here's the question:
can you redeem it? It is something that is טהור tahor that
is קדוש קדושת דמים. kadosh kedushas damim. So הני- hani now you're
getting why we discussed this. That works להך לישנא דאמר רב אושעיא
טמאים נפדים טהורים אין נפדים. lehach lishna de'amar Rav Oshaya tmeiyim nifdim
tehorim ein nifdim. According to the version that רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya
said that you can redeem טמא tamei things but not טהור tahor
things, so it works. That's how you can sanctify the olives and
the wheat and it never was fit to be eaten. שפיר, shapir,
it's good. אלא להך לישנא דאמר אפילו טהורים נפדים, ela lehach lishna
de'amar afilu tehorim nifdim, but according to the version that he says
that even טהור tahor things can be redeemed, וליפרקינהו. lifrikinhu. Why aren't
you- you could be פודה podeh it. So the same רב אושעיא
Rav Oshaya that said that this מנחה mincha is not food and
never fit to be eaten according to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, right?
And the only scenario is when you sanctified the stuff from the
very beginning, how does that work with the רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
that says that you're able to redeem it at that earlier stage?
So it should be fit to be eaten. So the גמרא Gemara
first gives the easy answer. The גמרא Gemara says, השתא מיהא לא
פריק. hashta mi lo parik. Okay, so- so
okay, in theory you could redeem it, but you didn't redeem it.
So maybe we just judge it not by what in theory could
be done but practically. Practically this stuff was sanctified when it was
still growing and even though in theory it could be redeemed, through
its actual life there was never a moment when it could be
eaten. But now the גמרא Gemara is gonna say aha, but according
to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon what could be done theoretically is relevant.
So the גמרא Gemara says, וכיון דאי בעי פריק ליה, vekivan de'iba'i
parik lei, but one minute, since you if you wanted to you
could redeem
it, שמעינן ליה לרבי שמעון sham'inan lei leRebbi Shimon דאמר כל העומד
לפדות כפדוי דמי. de'amar kol ha'omed lifdos kepadu dami. Anything that is
fit to be redeemed is like it's redeemed. Now, it doesn't literally
mean like it's redeemed that you go ahead and use it for
non-הקדש hekdesh purposes,
but it means in a consideration of this, do we say the
fit was- food was fit to be eaten? Since it could have
been redeemed, we look at that as theoretically possible to be eaten.
Where did רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say this?
דתניא, detanya, we learn a ברייתא. braisa. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon
omer, פרה מטמאי טומאת אוכלין. para metamei tumas ochlin. The פרה אדומה
para aduma you shechted it and you know, you're going to burn
it and make the ashes for the- you know, for sprinkling, and
nevertheless you have this dead cow that's almost ready to be burned
and he says if something touched it, it would have- you know,
some שרץ sheretz touched it, it would become טמא, tamei, it would
receive the טומאה tuma of foodstuff. Why is this cow fit to
be eaten? I mean, you know it's a- קרבן Korban and now
you have to or whatever it is it's קדוש Kadosh and now
you have to burn it. So why? הוה והיתה לו שעת הכושר
Hava vehayta lo sha'at hakoasher because it had a moment where it
could be eaten. What is that moment?
ואמר ריש לקיש Ve'amar Reish Lakish and now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
said to explain this, אמר היה רבי שמעון, Amar haya Rabbi Shimon,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon used to say פרה נפדית על גבי מערכתה
Para nifdit al gabei ma'arachta that even when the cow, the פרה
אדומה Para adumah was there on the on the like
wood ready on the fire, whatever that's called, the wood pile, ready
to be lit on fire up to the last minute you could
redeem it. Okay and now that's an interesting question because פרה אדומה
Para adumah is not a קרבן Korban exactly, it's like a קרבן,
Korban, but it actually it's not brought in the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, does it have קדושת דמים, Kedushat damim, does it have קדושת
הגוף, Kedushat haguf, that's a whole discussion. And he says רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would say it's basically like a type of קדושת דמים,
Kedushat damim, קדושת בדק הבית Kedushat bedek habayit and you could redeem
it up to the last minute and because theoretically it could be
redeemed it's considered food. So oh my god, it's not sometimes we
make like analogies and you could find a way to make it
different, but here רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon explicitly in terms of the
question of is something considered food because it's קדוש Kadosh and can't
be eaten says if in theory it could be redeemed then that
makes it considered food. So that would really raise a question to
your scenario about a מנחה Mincha that has never a moment that
is fit to be eaten. So let's take a look. הכי השתא.
Hachi hashtah. How can you make the comparison? Looked like a good
comparison to me. בשלמא פרה עומדת לפדות היא. Bishlama para omedet lifdot
hi.
By a case of פרה אדומה Para adumah that's something that it
not only is it theoretically possible to redeem but like that potential
is always there
in the offing. Like we're always weighing the possibility to redeem it.
Really? Like פרה אדומה? Para adumah? Like you just went through the
whole process you're looking for you're considering the possibility of redeeming it?
And the answer is yes. Why? שאם מצא אחרת נאה הימנה מצוה
לפדותה She'im matza acheret na'ah mimenah mitzvah lifdotah
because actually if even until the last minute you found a more
beautiful פרה אדומה Para adumah then you should redeem this and use
the other one. Like it's a little funny why do why do
they have to be competing? Why don't you use both? Have more
ashes. Anyway, but that's the point, okay. There there's an idea of
always looking for the better one. Like the person who's dating and
always got his eye out to see if there's somebody else he
should be dating. There so there it's like really more along the
lines of the potential of the possibility of being redeemed. Okay. אלא
הני מנחות מצוה לפדותן? Ela hani menachot mitzvah lifdotan? But in case
of a מנחה Mincha there's no idea of looking for a better
one and then redeeming it etc. So trying to make a very
subtle distinction that for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even though רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says that something has the potential to be redeemed it's
considered edible and מטמא טומאת אוכלין Mitamei tumat ochalin maybe he only
meant it by פרה אדומה Para adumah where we're looking out for
that possibility. But normally by the case of the מנחה Mincha he
wouldn't say it. So we can have a מנחה Mincha that you
sanctified yes while it was still olives on the tree and wheat,
yes you're allowed to redeem it and it's possible to redeem it
but as long as you haven't we're arguing that even for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's not yet considered edible and food. Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara says והלן לפני זריקה. Vehalan lifnei zerika. But
one minute, remember רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself gave the example of
two types of meat that was left over whether it was considered
fit to be eaten or not. Okay. והלן Vehalan meat of a
קרבן. Korban. לפני זריקה Lifnei zerika if it became left over till
the next day and you never threw the blood, so so that
is considered to be not never fit to be eaten and not
food. But one minute says the גמרא Gemara דמצוה למזרקי. Demitzve lemizrakei.
There there's actually a מצוה Mitzvah to sprinkle the blood. דאי בעי
זריק De'iba zarik and you have the ability to sprinkle. וקתני דאין
מטמא טומאת אוכלין. Vektani de'ein mitamei tumat ochalin.
Okay now that is a problem just comparing the two רבי שמעוןs,
Rabbi Shimon right? This doesn't even get to the רבי אושעיא Rabbi
Oshaya claim about the מנחה. Mincha. Forget the מנחה. Mincha. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon by the פרה Para said because you can redeem it
it's food. And here by the קרבן Korban he said that if
you don't sprinkle the blood and you leave it over to the
next day it wasn't food because it was never fit to be
eaten. Well I don't get it. The פרה Para is considered fit
to be eaten because in theory you could redeem it. The meat
should be considered fit to be eaten because you actually are obligated
to sprinkle the blood. So that seems like a good question. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha bemai
askinan שלא היתה שהות ביום למזרקי. shelo hayta shahut bayom limizrakei.
And so first it makes a very like narrow היכי תמצי. Hechay
temtah. You slaughtered the
קרבן Korban with a minute before שקיעה Shkiah and therefore you didn't
have a moment to throw the blood. Therefore it never had the
potential to have the blood thrown. אבל Aval so the גמרא Gemara
says אבל היתה לו שהות ביום מאי. Aval hayta lo shahut bayom
mai. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't buy this. So you, so you're
at to tell me that it's a very special case. But if
you had שחטד shechted it a few minutes before that actually even
though the blood was never sprinkled it would be able to be
food. So מה מטמא טומאת אוכלין mai metamei tumat ochlin then it
would be food, it could become טמא? tamei? אדקתני לן לאחר זריקה
מטמא טומאת אוכלין. adkatani lan leachar zerika metamei tumat ochlin. So why
when it was looking for a case of sacrificial meat that stayed
over, it only gave the case where you sprinkled the blood and
then you let the meat stay over? It should have given a
much bigger חדוש. chidush. ליפלוג בדידיה, liflog bedidei, you could even make
a distinction within the case of not sprinkling the blood. במה דברים
אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when does not sprinkling the blood mean that
this isn't food because it was never fit to be eaten? שלא
היתה שהות ביום, shelo hayta sheut bayom, when it was right before
sunset and you didn't even have the opportunity. אבל היתה לו שהות
ביום מטמא טומאת אוכלין. aval hayta lo sheut bayom metamei tumat ochlin.
But if you had, if it was earlier in the day, it
would become טמא. tamei. So it's right, you know when רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says if the blood wasn't thrown, it's not food, it
does not sound like you didn't have an opportunity to throw it.
And if it was really true that if once you had an
opportunity it would be considered food, then you needed to have said
that. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי קאמר, hachi nami ka'amar,
yeah, that's what he means. Okay, not really very believable. לן קודם
שיהיה ראוי לזריקה, lan kodem sheyiheye rauy lizerika, if it slept over,
you know, before it was ever possible to sprinkle the blood, אינו
מטמא טומאת אוכלין, eino metamei tumat ochlin, it's not. לאחר שיהיה ראוי
לזריקה, leachar sheyiheye rauy lizerika, but if it was not if the
blood was sprinkled, if it was possible to sprinkle the blood, מטמא
טומאת אוכלין. metamei tumat ochlin. Okay, so again, not really sounds at
all like what he's saying, but we're trying to say, ah, but
it's now we have an internal problem in רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is מטמא טומאת אוכלין metamei tumat
ochlin because in theory you could redeem it, and this meat is
not even though you have a מצוה mitzvah to be זורק zorek
the blood. So what we're saying right now is we're reading him
to say not did you זורק zorek the blood or not זורק
zorek the blood, but did you have the opportunity to be זורק
zorek the blood or not, that's what determines it.
So now the גמרא, Gemara, okay, we're not done. והפיגול בין בקדשי
קדשים בין בקדשים קלים דמצוה למיזרקיה. vehapigul bein bekadshei kodashim bein bekodashim
kalim demitzvah lemizrekeih. So now not the case of לן, lan, the
case of פיגול. pigul. When you had a פיגול pigul thought by
קדשי קדשים kadshei kodashim or קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. So before you
had that פיגול pigul thought, there was a מצוה mitzvah to do
it the right
way, okay? ואי בעי זריק ve'ei ba'ei zarik and you could have
thrown the blood if you look at רש"י Rashi בדבור המתחיל פיגול,
bedibur hamatchil pigul, all right? So you שחטד shechted it, it's not
yet fit to be eaten, okay, but at this stage because you
haven't been throwing the blood, but there's a מצוה mitzvah to throw
the blood the right way. So until you, so in that moment
between שחיטה shechitah and you catch the blood and you're walking it
to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, we should consider the meat fit to be
eaten because you have a מצוה mitzvah to end the קרבן Korban
the right way. You wound up ending it with פיגול, pigul, I
get it, but before you ended it with פיגול, pigul, it was
theoretically fit to be eaten because you should have ended it the
right way. So the גמרא Gemara says וקתני דאינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין,
vekatani de'eino metamei tumat ochlin, it's not מטמא טומאת אוכלין. metamei tumat
ochlin.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו דפיגול בזריקה, mai lav depigul
bezerika, are we not talking, top of קב עמוד א, kuf bet
amud aleph, are we not talking that you had a פיגול pigul
thought when you were sprinkling the blood and you had all that
time from שחיטה shechitah until sprinkling that it was theoretically fit to
be eaten because you could have done the blood the right way,
sprinkled the blood the right way? So that shows that the theoretical
possibility doesn't work. גמרא Gemara says לא דפיגול בשחיטה. lo depigul beshechitah.
No, no, no, when he says פיגול pigul it's not, it's when
you פיגול pigul at the שחיטה, shechitah, so from the very moment
it became meat, it was not fit, it was already פיגול. pigul.
So the גמרא's Gemara's going to ask the same question it asked:
if that's true, then you should have told us the חדוש chidush
that there's some types of פיגול pigul that it is considered food.
אבל פיגול בזריקה מאי, aval pigul bezerika mai, so what are you
going to tell me? If you had the פיגול pigul thought later
at the זריקה zerika הכי נמי דמטמא טומאת אוכלין hachi nami demetamei
tumat ochlin then it would be food because between שחיטה shechitah and
זריקה zerika theoretically you could have done it the right way and
you could have eaten it, so why not say that? אדקתני פיגול
במנחה מטמא טומאת אוכלין, adkatani pigul beminchah metamei tumat ochlin, rather than
just saying oh if it's a מנחה minchah that's מטמא metamei because
that started off as flour and oil. So ליפלוג בדידיה, liflog bedidei,
why not tell me there's ways that even an animal פיגול pigul
can be considered food? במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when is
an animal פיגול pigul not food? דפיגול בשחיטה, depigul beshechitah, that you
had a פיגול pigul thought at שחיטה, shechitah, so from the moment
it became meat it was not fit. אבל פיגול בזריקה מטמא טומאת
אוכלין, aval pigul bezerika metamei tumat ochlin, but if your פיגול pigul
thought was only when you were sprinkling the blood, then it is,
can become food because between the שחיטה shechitah and the זריקה zerika
you could have theoretically done it the right way and you had
a מצוה mitzvah to do it the right way. So again, sounds
really, really like the theoretical ability to be זורק zorek the דם
dam does not matter here, but the גמרא Gemara is going to
say no, we are going to claim there's a reason it wanted
to give מנחה minchah as the case that works. פיגול במנחה איצטריכא
ליה. pigul beminchah itztericha lei. It wanted to give you the example
of the פיגול pigul of the... מנחה mincha rather than the example
of being a פיגול pigul at זריקה. zrika. דאף על גב דפיגול
בקמיצה דקומץ במנחה כשחיטה דמי אפילו מהכא מטמא טומאת אוכלין De’af al
gav de’pigul b’kmitza de’komitz b’mincha k’shchita damei afilu mehacha mitamei tumas ochlin
הואיל וחזי לשעת הכושר מעיקרא. hois v’chazi l’shas kosher mei’ikara. So he
says, we wanted to contrast, we could have contrasted שחיטה shchita of
an animal of פיגול, pigul, which it's not food, to the זריקה
zrika where it is because in theory you could be
זורק zorek the דם dam the right way. We could have done
that. But what we wanted more to do is contrast שחיטה shchita
of an animal to קמיצה kmitza of a מנחה. mincha. קמיצה kmitza
of a מנחה mincha is like the שחיטה shchita of the animal,
right? It separates the parts, it sort of gets the part that
you're going to put on the מזבח. mizbeach. Those two are made
analogous. So although שחיטה shchita of an animal is no good because
from the moment it becomes meat it's not, it's
פיגול, pigul, קמיצה kmitza which is like שחיטה, shchita, קמיצה kmitza of
a מנחה mincha is good because the flour and the oil were
edible beforehand. So that's why we made that contrast, but אין הכי
נמי, ein hachi nami, פיגול pigul by the זריקה zrika would also
be food because theoretically you could have done the זריקה zrika correctly.
So what has the גמרא Gemara said? We'll just read one more
line which is a more gratifying answer. Okay, besides the whole question
about Rabbi Oshia's claim about a מנחה mincha and talking about sanctifying
it when it was still wheat and olives and whether you are
able to redeem it or not able to redeem it, we have
a seeming contradiction in Rabbi Shimon himself. Rabbi Shimon saying that
the פרה אדומה parah adumah is food because it could be redeemed
and Rabbi Shimon saying that these cases of פיגול pigul and לן
lan and all these types of cases are not food, even though
there was a מצוה mitzvah to do it right. And until now
the גמרא Gemara is basically saying אין הכי נמי ein hachi nami
and making them all special cases. Okay, and but אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami, if you had an opportunity to do it right,
it would be considered food by these קרבנות, korbanot, by you know
by the case of לינה lina or פיגול pigul or whatever. Now
we'll read just רב אשי Rav Ashi and we'll wrap up with
this for today, who gives a more gratifying answer. אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, said רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אמינא לה לשמעתא קמיה
דרב נחמן, Amiseh l’shmaita kmei de’Rav Nachman, I said this over in
front of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and here's the explanation. אפילו תימא
לן ממש, Afilu teima lan mamash, even if it was not just
you shechted, you didn't have an opportunity to sprinkle the blood. You
had an opportunity to sprinkle the blood. Okay, אפילו תימא דפיגול בזריקה
Afilu teima de’pigul b’zrika and
even if you did the פיגול pigul at the זריקה zrika and
you had and from the שחיטה shchita to the זריקה zrika you
had the opportunity to end it correctly. Nevertheless, דאי בעי פריק אמרינן
אי בעי הוה זריק לא אמרינן. de’ibai parik amrinan ibai hava zarik
lo amrinan. This is such a more gratifying answer. That you
could have redeemed it and therefore it's food, that we say, that
is what we were discussing about the מנחה mincha and that's what
we were discussing about the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. The ability to
redeem it is seen as something easy and accessible and so on.
Whereas you could have been זורק zorek the דם, dam, that is
not. Now what is the difference between those two? So, so רש"י
Rashi says the following. דאי בעי פריק אמרינן, De’ibai parik amrinan, this
is about רש"י Rashi ten lines down in the narrow lines. The
fact that you could redeem it is seen as that potential we
see right here and alive. דמחוסר פדיה לאו כמעשה דמי דברים בעלמא
נינהו De’mechusar pidya lav k’maiseh damei d’varim b’alma ninhu that being פודה
podeh something is just words, I'm transferring the קדושה kedusha from this
to the money. Okay, so the fact that just by words you
can change its status, we see that potential already here and it's
considered to be theoretically fit to be eaten because you just have
to say the right words and then you'll be able to eat
it. Okay, דאי בעי זריק לא אמרינן, De’ibai zarik lo amrinan, but
that you could throw the blood, that's a whole act. So a
whole act like yeah you could change the status, right, if grandma
had wheels she'd be a trolley car. Like if you were זורק
zorek it the right way, if you do an act and change
the status, but right now that's not the status. So when do
we say let's look at the here and now and judge it
by that? That's if the only thing that will change its status
is an actual act. Until that act happens, we're judging it by
its current state. And therefore its current state is not edible, not
food. But the cases of the מנחה mincha that we were had
a problem with and the case of the פרה אדומה parah adumah
where just by words you could redeem, that is the case where
Rabbi Shimon says we will look at it if it's possible to
be redeemed, we will look at it as edible and as food
even right now. Okay, we'll end here for today.